<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the supreme authority the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England. The humble proposals of Edmund Felton Gent..</title>
            <author>Felton, Edmond.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B22908</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F663</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 190.g.13[204]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232569</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99888952</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99888952</idno>
            <idno type="VID">194006</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B22908)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 194006)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C29:2[204])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the supreme authority the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England. The humble proposals of Edmund Felton Gent..</title>
                  <author>Felton, Edmond.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.C. for M.S.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Edmund Felton.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Plantations --  Northern Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Trade regulation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Economic conditions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:194006:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Supreme Authority the Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The humble Propoſals of <hi>Edmund Felton</hi> Gent.</head>
            <opener>That which he humbly offers is,</opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW</hi> Ireland <hi>and all other Engliſh Plantations may multiply and increaſe much more trading then now is, or hath been for many years; and all the Souldiers in</hi> Ireland <hi>paid, and other juſt debts, and yet not any mony for ſo doing disburſed by the States, but to their great advantage; yea many hundred thouſand pounds hereby to be brought into their Treaſury: And for which ſo doing, in 1601. is a Precedent upon record: by which courſe the late Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>then carryed on the War in</hi> Ireland, <hi>with ſmall taxes to the Subjects, and as the ſtate of</hi> Ireland <hi>now ſtands, by the preſcribed courſe following,</hi> Ireland <hi>in few years may be fully planted with Engliſh-men and women, all which may be accompliſhed as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. If it ſhall pleaſe the States to cauſe 200000 <hi>l.</hi> or more forthwith to be coyned in Occamy money, as they do in <hi>Holland,</hi> and the late Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did for <hi>Ireland</hi> in 1601. and to paſſe there for currant coyne; every hundred pound thus coyned, to be in half-crowns, ſhillings, ſixpences, and ſmaller pieces. The mettle, ſtamping and ſilvering of 100 <hi>l.</hi> of the ſaid coyne, will not ſtand the State in above five pound; three hundred pound of which coyne any of the Inhabitants in <hi>Ireland</hi> to have for 100 <hi>l.</hi> in Gold or Silver, which there, is as good to them as gold or ſilver, there paſſing currant by Act of Parliament. The States hereby gets clear for every three hundred pound thus coyned to paſſe in <hi>Ireland,</hi> eighty five pounds. By this courſe not any man there living can be prejudiced, but much bettered in his eſtate; for any man whoſe ſtock in mony there (or here if he goe for <hi>Ireland</hi>) be but 10 <hi>l.</hi> he ſhall have for it 30 <hi>l.</hi> in the new coyne, for 20 <hi>l.</hi> to have 60 <hi>l.</hi> for 100 <hi>l.</hi> in gold or ſilver, 300 <hi>l.</hi> and ſo proportionably. Thus every dealer herein trebles his ſtocke, and by this meanes when they are in <hi>Ireland</hi> it will keep them there; and the Souldiers there who hath land given them for their Arrears, will by this courſe be enabled to keep their Land and to ſtocke it, if 100 <hi>l.</hi> or 50 <hi>l.</hi> of the ſaid coyne be lent to ſuch Souldiers as have wife and children, for one year gratis, and for the years following they ſhall keep the ſaid mony, to pay to the State <hi>5l.</hi> or 6 <hi>l.</hi> for 100 <hi>l.</hi> within two years will pay the States what they diſburſed; and as long after as the ſaid 100 <hi>l.</hi> or 50 <hi>l.</hi> ſhall by any be detained, to pay the rate of as aforeſaid to the States uſe, which will come clearly unto them.</p>
            <p>The ſaid coyne likewiſe to paſſe currant in all other Engliſh Plantations and no where elſe, and upon the ſame termes as in <hi>Ireland;</hi> by this courſe both the gold and ſilver in Engliſh Plantations will alſo be brought into this Nation, to the great in riching of the States, and the Inhabitants both in <hi>Ireland</hi> and the ſaid Plantations. And for that this is not a coyne to be horded up, it will cauſe the more Trading, Planting, tilling and ſtocking of ground, and ſo conſequently the more imployment for the poor.</p>
            <p>If objected, How ſhall any come for <hi>England,</hi> and here travell and follow their occaſions?</p>
            <p>It's anſwered, That whoſo hath juſt cauſe ſo to do a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what Port-town ſoever he ſhall land, where the chiefeſt of able and honeſt men to be Treaſurers, there to have 20 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>l.</hi> or leſſe, bringing treble the coyne as they had when went for <hi>Ireland</hi> (and they to have ſixpence in the pound) but not any man to have above 20 <hi>l.</hi> in ſilver (nor that if ten pound may ſerve for his occaſions) to travell and returne back. <hi>Spain</hi> and other Nations who are farre more richer in gold and ſilver then <hi>England,</hi> have much of Copper and Occamy mony which goeth currantly amongſt them in their dominions.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Alſo a great revenue for ſome years may as thus come unto the States, if they pleaſe to lend 100 <hi>l.</hi> or more of the ſaid coyne to Families that will go for <hi>Ireland,</hi> having a ſtock of Corne and Cattle, who wants mony, and willing to farme Lands in <hi>Ireland</hi> of the States, which ſo doing will cauſe much people to go to inhabit there.</p>
            <p>And as for ſtrangers that ſhall trade in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or any of the Engliſh Plantations, to trade with Commodities for Commodities, or to give gold or ſilver for what they ſhall buy there, but not to buy any Commodity with this States new coyne, but for their expences for meat, drink and lodging whileſt they are in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or the Engliſh Plantations, if they give gold or ſilver, to have treble the ſumme of the Treaſurers there, which will be a means to prevent bringing in of the like coyne.</p>
            <p n="3">3 If objected, that if there were ſuch a coyne the <hi>Dutch</hi> and other Nations would bring in aboundance of the like, and carry away Commodities of great value for it; which may be prevented as aforeſaid and followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Strangers to barter Commodity for commodity, unleſſe they bring ſilver. Secondly, if there be as ſtrict a Law for counterfeiting or making any of the ſaid coyne as the Act of Parliamnt is for ſtealing away any Maide under 21 years of age, not any will dare to venture (to be as a ſlave all his life) to make any of the ſaid coyne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whatſoever goods ſhall be brought into <hi>Ireland</hi> or any of the Engliſh Plantations to have the Governours ſeal ſet thereon as ſoon as landed, and what goods ſoever are to be opened for ſale in that City or Town, the ſaid Governour or chief Officer to appoint ſome honeſt men to be at the opening thereof, to ſee if any coyne be conveyed therein, and if any Lead ſhould be brought to <hi>Ireland</hi> or any of the ſaid Plantations, then the Governour or chief Officer in view of the people where it ſhall be landed, to ſet a ſtampe on each ſow of Lead, which is not to be melted in the ſaid City or Town till the Governour or chief Officer, ſhall ſend ſome honeſt men to view the ſtampe and to be at the melting thereof, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with an Iron ladle to ſee if there be any coyne therein conveyed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That there be the like courſe of ſearching of any caske wherein ſhall be wine, oil, or any other Commodity whatſoever, and that at their firſt landing if any liquid Commodity, and before it be houſed.</p>
            <p>And if any of the ſaid Commodities by whole ſale be carried to other Cities or Townes, the chief Magiſtrate there to ſet his marke or ſeal on the ſaid Pack, in the preſence of ſome honeſt Townſmen, to the end (if not opened preſently) that it ſhall not be opened till the ſaid Magiſtrate ſhall ſend ſome honeſt men to be at the opening thereof. And to prevent favour or affecting any, if it may be thought fitting, the ſaid Overſeers to take this Oath following, (either voluntarily or given by the Magiſtrate) <hi>I A.B. deſire of God I may not proſper in this life nor any thing I take in hand, if I prove deceitfull in this my undertaking for the Common-wealths good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſons conduceing hereunto, conſidering how this Nation is much impoveriſhed in gold and ſilver, ſince theſe troubles; As
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, by ſending many hundred thouſands of pounds out of <hi>England</hi> into <hi>Holland</hi> and other Countries.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, the treaſure cannot but be great that hath been hid this time of warre, and to be beleeved, moſt of the hiders have loſt their lives before they could diſcover where they hid it.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, many who now have much treaſure, will not be known of it for fear of Taxes.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly, it cannot but be a great prejudice to this Nation, if thoſe that go for <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſhall carry what gold or ſilver they can thither in this impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhing time.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To prevent which, the Propoſer humbly conceives this way of a new coyne for <hi>Ireland</hi> and all other Engliſh Plantations, will wonderfully inrich that land, and make the people better able to pay their Taxes in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ireland</hi> hath now been this twleve years very chargeable to <hi>England</hi> by reaſon of the late troubles, and not any thing profitable by way of Trading to this Nation, (ſince which troubles, hundreds of thouſands of pounds have been ſent thither) all which time, the Engliſh inhabitants hath conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly endured under great ſufferings. If now for the like time men would with as much patience content themſelves to have this preſcribed new coyne if but for 12 years, it would be the cauſe that <hi>Ireland</hi> would almoſt be fully inhabited, and have plenty of Corne, Cattle, Sheep, and all other neceſſary food, which as the Apoſtle ſaith is ſufficient, exhorting the people of God to learn to be content therewith. But if not but by covetouſneſſe men will be rich in gold and ſilver, he plainly tels them it is an enterance into ſtrife, and many fooliſh and and noy ſome luſts which drown men in perdition and deſtruction; as for thoſe covetous ones who think gain godlineſſe, the Apoſtle tels them no, it is not ſo, requiring all that fear God to withdraw themſelves from ſuch, ſaying, godlineſſe with content is great gain, 1 <hi>Tim. 6. ch.</hi> and for men ſo to be, it would be the New birth, and much rejoyce them to ſee their Brothers and Neighbours to thrive by them. But the covetous man thinks all too little for himſelf, which <hi>Solomon</hi> confirmes (ſaying <hi>Prov. 1. 19.) He that is greedy of gain taketh away the life of the owners thereof.</hi> It is content, not wealth, is mans happineſſe in this life.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>In all which the Propoſer humbly ſubmits unto your Honours moſt grave wiſdome, Edmund Felton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. C.</hi> for <hi>M. S.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
